Another critical element of the board effectiveness is
the board evaluation that I have just briefly
described.
And what is that process?
The process sees the board appointing a consultant.
Sometimes some boards decide to do this by
themselves but I can assure you that this
is not as effective as appointing a consultant.
Indeed, the codes of corporate governance require that
the board appoints an external consultant to do
this periodically.
For some of the regulated entities, the frequency
is annual.
For some others, they are allowed to do
this in a three-year circle.
So what is being evaluated?
The structure and composition of the board is
being evaluated.
The operations and effectiveness of the board is
The board's oversight of strategy and risk management
as well as compliance.
The board's oversight of transparency and disclosure as
well as the board's oversight of the corporate
citizenship of the entity.
So what happens at the end of the
day is that all of these indices that
are evaluated, the consultants will identify the areas
of strength, the areas of compliance and the
areas of gap that need to be ameliorated
by the board.
The consultants will also make recommendations on how
these gaps identified can be bridged and the
board will then thereafter have an implementation plan
that will see it's implementing the recommendations that
the consultant has made to fill the gaps.
As we round off, we identify or go
into the areas, the red flag areas that
indicate that the board is veering towards ineffectiveness.
If the board has an opaque director selection
process whereby it's not clear to onlookers how
the board appoints or selects directors, if the
chair of the board is ineffective, if the
chair of the board is overbearing or the
CEO themselves are overbearing, if you have ineffective
or dysfunctional directors and the board doesn't have
a clear path to existing directors from the
board, if meetings lack focus, so if the
board directors attend a board meeting and there
isn't sufficient clarity on what exactly the board
was trying to achieve, that is a sign
of ineffectiveness and is a major red flag.
If there is a poor manual reporting system
that leads to information asymmetry so that the
executives know much more about the business than
the board does, there's clearly a problem.
If meetings are time-wasting, so the agenda
is overloaded, very unclear or loaded with matters
that shouldn't even concern the board at all.
If the committee system is ineffective, so we've
described effective committees, so sometimes boards have committees
just to fulfil all righteousness and the committees
come to the board with recommendations based on
their findings or their deliberations and the board
re-opens the matters that it has delegated
to the committees, then really and truly the
committee system is ineffective.
Where there is groupthink, meaning that there isn't
sufficient diversity on the board, then that's also
a red flag.
So for instance you have an all-male
board, or I dare say an all-female
board, even though that is not a very
common occurrence in this part of the world.
But if you have a board, for instance,
maybe it's a board with a bank and
all the directors are bankers or people with
financial services experience, then that board is likely
to be ineffective because it's not a true
representation of the society that really and truly
the bank is serving.
If the secretariat is ineffective, because the secretariat,
the committee secretary has a critical role to
play in board effectiveness, so if the secretariat
is ineffective, it is most likely to impact
on the board's effectiveness itself.
We mentioned tenure for directors, so where you
have on-tenure directors, meaning that the board
doesn't have sufficient opportunity to replenish itself or
to refresh its membership, then that's also a
red flag.
Where succession planning is not in place, and
this is not just succession planning at the
level of management or the other members of
the organisation, but succession planning even at the
level of the board.
So for instance, the board doesn't have a
clear path to selecting a replacement for an
existing chair, that is a recipe for failure.
Or where there isn't a clear path as
to how disputes will be resolved, because the
human beings, the individuals, like I said earlier
on, they come onto the board with their
own ego, their own background, so occasionally they
are bound to the friction, they are bound
to the conflict.
So if the board doesn't have a clear
path to how these conflicts or disputes are
resolved, it's also a clear path to failure.
Where the board is too large or too
small, recall that I said that the Nigerian
Code of Corporate Governance does not specify a
minimum or maximum number of directors, but the
board, in its wisdom, should be able to
determine that this is the right size.
But the other guidelines, the other corporate governance
guidelines, especially the CBN guidelines, actually specifies a
maximum and a minimum number.
Where the board is too large or too
small, it can also impact on its effectiveness,
because if it's too small, you then have
the probability of a dominant personality on the
board.
Where the board is made up of directors
that are only looking out for their own
interests, especially where they don't declare such interests.
And finally, where the board doesn't have a
performance management mechanism, either for measuring its own
performance, but more especially for measuring the performance
and giving feedback through management.